welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
so let's do some check-ins I like to do
emotional check-ins at the beginning of
these now to kind of ground myself in
authenticity I feel a little nervous
it's like maybe 45 percent just like
bubbling up right here and that's
associated with or adjacent to that like
this delicious thumos talking to Jack
earlier and just riffing with him about
the history of certain spaces on the
internet was quite exciting so welcome
to the stoah I am the Stewart of the
stoic Peter Lindberg and I'm viewing the
stoah as a place that is stewarded by a
stoic but not necessarily a place to
practice and talk about stoicism that
will surely happen Here I am viewing it
as a digital campfire for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge of this moment and I'm
inviting all these cool guests coming in
experimenting with different psycho
technologies beneath the ROI was in the
earlier machine a psycho technology
playground and it's like my mind just
got like zapped afterwards and
everyone's like you couldn't think I
mentioned I see people talking about
epic beard I think a good psycho
technology just to sit in silent
meditation just stare at Jack Murphy's
beard and just you know get the thaw
most that comes from it so we have Jack
Murphy on today and Jack is a leader
organizer of something called the
liminal order he's the host of a podcast
called Jack Murphy live and the author
of a book called Democrat to deplorable
and his podcast I was telling to I was
talking to him about this beforehand
it's like he has this like a certain
quality and aesthetics to it I quite
like and his guest selection there's a
certain like kind of edginess like a
correct edginess
he has like delicious tacos on bronze a
pervert and yeah so the sense-making
mentions like Jordan Hall and John rabe
and whatnot
so I definitely recommend everyone check
that out
so today jack is going to share his
thoughts on the liminal war and the rise
of info militias and behind it to him in
a moment so how's it gonna work is he's
gonna share his thoughts and then you
know maybe I'll warm em up with some
questions and if you have a question for
jack just write it in the chat box and
then I'll call on you when you can
unmute yourself and read it to Jack
alternatively just indicate if you want
me to read on your behalf and I will do
so so that being said I will allow Jack
to unmute himself and hand it over to
him thanks
how's everybody doing I'm very excited
actually to be here because I've been
watching Peter for a little bit I think
I first came across him when the culture
war white paper came out and I found out
to be fascinating and I've also been
sort of running in some of the same
circles as Peter by talking to Jordan
and John and John Robb as he said and
Jim rut and I have had some some
dialogues over the last couple of years
as well and so I'm actually pretty
excited to be here but I - and we're
getting a little sense of nerves and
that I think comes from one just being
happy to be here but - I am the extent
of my philosophy background in education
is limited to like intro to political
philosophy in college and then I took a
Marx class and then from there I just
trans transferred into economics so I'm
not not like a philosopher by any means
and there's certainly gaps in my
academic understanding of the world but
I would consider myself to be sort of on
the in the trenches and sort of on the
ground and and sort of discovering
philosophy through practice and trying
to learn the terms of the things that
we're discovering and trying to sort of
fit ourselves and when I say we I mean
the the guys the men of the limo order
and sort of my social media audience fit
us into the world and what's happening
here
a lot a lot of what we do is I don't
wanna say it's reactionary because that
word has a lot of a lot of weight to it
but we're sort of adapting and just
moving on the fly and then I'm learning
from you guys and from other people what
the big words are that describe what
we're doing and John John Rob especially
in Jordan Hall especially have been very
helpful in helping give me context and
also help give me some direction so I
first discovered Jordan talking about
the blue church and the situational
assessment I'm sure many of you read
back in 20 16 or 17 or so where I began
to understand the legacy media the
top-down centralized communication
structures of the past the one-to-many
communication and the total domination
of
active control from a small cabal of
people who wanted to to manage us and
everyone else then and and also
understanding the value that that
brought in terms of social cohesion
where we all sort of believed and could
believe in a story that we held in our
head and and United around that imagined
order that gives us a society and
civilization but as I you know got to
know Jordan better and got to understand
the material better and got to
understand where we were in the world
you know I'm understanding that we're
now talking many-to-many and the
centralized communication information
flow has been disrupted in a major way
and watching the the evolution of
decentralized both political movements
as well as information networks has has
been at once educational and
inspirational and motivational for me
because it did reveal gaps and it does
reveal sort of the problems and things
that we're facing in the future and I
participated early on in a him
decentralized information network called
the manosphere I don't know how many of
you are familiar with that but it was a
phenomenon that bubbled up from the
deepest and darkest corners of the
internet over time starting in the
2005-2010 range and it was just it was a
response to radical feminism and some
crazy super out there ideas that people
found to be oppressive and it was just a
way for people to link up network share
notes and information and develop a
cohesion in a story for themselves and
and even just on the ground tactical
ways to improve their lives and and that
evolved over time and there were other
movements sort of like a gamergate which
is another decentralized political
movement that happened I'm sure some of
you're familiar with that and then also
the canceled culture which is not my
friend it's not something I'm interested
in but that is a also another form of a
decentralized effort where people will
congregate around
common goal which in my case was like
getting myself getting me doxed and
fired from my whole job and it happens
to other people in certain other ways
and then those networks sort of
dissipate after that so I'm living I'm a
product of I'm learning about and sort
of experiencing on the ground at all
time this affective decentralized
information networks in decentralized
political movements and the talk of what
we what we want to talk about today is
this disturb info militia and I actually
just sort of first started writing about
that a couple of weeks ago it just kind
of came out in conversation and it had a
really nice ring to it and it really
summarized what we're doing in the lemon
order which is itself a decentralized
sense making apparatus and during this
time of Corona and kovat we have sort of
proven the thesis of little order which
is that we need to have our own sense
making apparatus our own ability to
discern what's right and what's wrong
and then to carry Jordans personal
sovereignty notions further you know
then then we want to take that
information and then we want to embody
it in what we're doing we want to embody
these ideals and we want to build the
integrity and the strength that we need
in order to embody those ideals and to
sort of move forward and what I've
discovered it using this word info
militias which was sort of offhand but
now have sort of gone back to sort of
look at the definitions behind info and
militias and to try to put it into a
framework I think we all know what
information is but a militia in
particular the definition of militia is
a military force that is raised from the
civil population to supplement a regular
army in an emergency and so it got me
thinking we're clearly in a state of
crisis in a number of different ways the
first one just obvious right now is
Corona and Cohen covert right
but larger than that we have a sense
making crisis we have a narrative crisis
we have a social cohesion crisis we have
community crisis we have a number we
have a loss of with the loss of
confidence and the may be the most
powerful crisis we're facing is a sense
of overwhelming complexity in the world
so there is an emergency a state of
emergency out there that it requires the
raising of a private army to both make
sense of and then to not only endure but
to thrive in this environment and this
is the fundamental notion behind the
liminal order is that we're living in a
crisis and we have to do things on our
own and so what we've seen during Corona
which I think has been for all the
negatives obviously there's too many to
list there have been some positives and
one of the positives is seeing how the
decentralized informations are
sense-making apparatus worldwide has
really stepped up I think and and there
are a number of different nodes out
there where people are able to do the
research do the analysis clear signal
from noise and come to a cohesive
understanding of either what the virus
is or what the government is going to do
that's been my main focus I don't really
know anything about viruses but I do
can't predict what the government is
going to do and so in the liminal order
for example we were in mid-february
we were already at a state of emergency
within the liminal order we had
recommended to all of our people that
they start stockpiling masks they you
know hydrochloric wean vitamin C you
know a million different things we were
really prepared because we are dedicated
to actually making sense of what's going
on out there in the world because we
realized that there is crisis and
complexity crisis of leadership you know
continuing on from 2008-2009 financial
crisis you know the corruption and
academia etc etc all those things that
you guys know about
so we knew that we had to be proactive
about going out and finding the
information that we needed in order to
survive basically this became an issue
you know obviously not millions people
are dying but you know it seemed like
and it is for many people matter of life
or death and the information that we're
getting from CDC and from the World
Health Organization and from you know
the administration and from corporations
not helpful not helpful enough by any
means and so the liminal order is a has
proven the thesis that there's a crisis
is a crisis of information and that in a
time of crisis - in order to supplement
the regular forces these militias need
to arise and they have arisen and they
have risen and the limit order is just
bought one of these info militias that
have risen up to fill the gap to make to
cover up for complexity it's make sense
and in our case we really are trying
then to carry it even a few steps
further and then go into the both
embodiment and integrity and choice of
how to live our lives and to sort of
represent the ideals that we have so
that was the the main thrust of why
Peter reached out to me was to talk
about the info militia term the other
theme that I wanted that that sort of is
overarching all of this is is the the
fact that we're at the end of the era of
indiscriminate connection right so
through internet social media World
Trade Organization NATO alliance
expansion and and and corporate
connections supply chains etc we did
there was a time period for the last 20
30 40 years we're connecting and our
reach and expansion was sort of the
number-one goal and there was you know
I'm calling it indiscriminate
connections and now we're seeing that
that era is over and that we're now
moving into an age of strategic
disconnection so all the value of just
running out and connecting with people
all over the world has been wrung out I
believe and now the next phase the next
leg up of value is going to be
and actually making strategic decisions
of disconnection and again liminal order
is embodying that we're living that
we've decided to step back away from
social media and the random connections
that can be made that way and to focus
our energy and relationship building and
networking within a high trust high
value Private Network that's got high
security and is committed to the same
goals so all this is in the same theme
the end of like this the end of the
expanding era is over and we're moving
now towards strategic disconnection and
as by way of example we saw Japan just
recently announced that they are
spending like two billion dollars to
figure out how to get businesses and
factories out of China and back into
into Japan so this is a process that's
just beginning sort of like an unwinding
of the great expansion era of the last
20 30 40 years and the the smart money
is figuring out ways to strategically
disconnect and to create a higher trust
higher value network and that's gonna be
trade government political networks
social media military alliances even
social distancing right and our regular
day to day relationships so those are
the general themes that Peter wanted to
talk about and you know I can talk about
any one of those dig down for four hours
on any one of those subjects there but I
just want to throw that out there and
sort of get the discussion started and
you know again thank you guys for having
me here it's very exciting and fun stuff
to talk about and I'm sure we're gonna
have a good discussion coming up after
this thank you very much Peter there you
go there's the intro very very cool yeah
that's a lot of good threads that are
coming up for me so a warm Jack up with
a few questions if you have questions
write in the chat box and I'll
eventually call on you to mute yourself
if you want me to read it on your behalf
just indicate that I'm gonna use my
discernment what questions Theresa they
might not be read in order and we might
not get to all the questions okay so the
first one just sort like a practical
um question and and I understand if you
don't want to answer all of these due to
secrecy or whatever but like how did the
liminal order start like how many
members like how do you like organize
like this like real brass tacks of it
sure
so we are just over 200 active members
we have most of them in the United
States but we're in seven countries
around the world three different
continents
it is it is technically and and will be
it's an all men's Network part that was
part of part of our answer that the
general theme is this is an answer to
the culture war we don't want to fight
culture war in public we don't want to
do social media battles we don't want to
participate in cancel culture our
philosophy is to step back strategically
disconnect build deep deep roots outside
of the glare of social media outside of
the public you know this is born out of
me being doxxed and me having my whole
life turned on its head I'm some of you
probably are unfamiliar but I was
working in charter schools I was the
executive director of charter schools
which they in themselves are also
decentralized networks that are an
evolution in the way that we do things
and one day an Tifa which is like this
radical left organization decided that
they wanted to Doc's my pen name so they
went to my employer and called me all
kinds of horrible names Nazi racist all
right none of which is true but their
whole goal was to get me fired so the
liminal order sort of born out of my
personal experience we want to step back
from social media we want to build a
high trust high value Private Network
with secure multiple forms of
communication we have a high highly
secure message system called wicker so
that's one way we have a forum which is
another way email list as well as United
States Postal Service so we have
multiple redundant overlapping
communication systems they're all based
in different countries with different
political risks and such - so if we get
shutdown on one
we will have other multiple channels of
communication and the general idea is
and and this is a partly a genesis of
working with Jordan is that we wanted to
improve our personal sovereignty and we
want to improve our ability to make
sense of the world to discern what's
what's right and what's wrong what's
good and what's bad and then we want the
power to to actually live that out and
so we work on meditation we work on
physical fitness we have physical
fitness standards we study things like
fourth-generation warfare with you know
naval officers and u.s. Naval Academy
professors we're studying logic right
now with college professor teaches logic
we've done cognitive behavioral therapy
so we're trying to trying to figure out
how to control our emotions how to think
more clearly how to understand the world
around us fourth-generation warfare very
important concept right now and then do
it in a community of men with the who
want to save the world basically
starting by improving ourselves then our
family then our community and if you can
get that far then maybe you can have
some impact on the nation or on the
national conversation so that's the
general gist and we have a waiting list
of 1,500 people and we've got the doors
closed because you know our growth is
meant to be strategic and it's a very
personal intense experience and so we're
gonna onboard people as we have the
capacity to take them on and so what's
coming up it's interesting so as you
mentioned and people some people might
know like I studied the culture war and
talk about mimetic tribes and one of
them I listed was the manosphere and you
and I were riffing off that before like
the kind of the history of it and my
read on the manosphere like not not the
current version but the one back in the
heyday was like it was like an
intersection between kind of three
different things like cultural politics
kind of like self-help and what would be
the other one there's something else
there but yeah at least those are two
intersection or masculinity
kind of the cultivation or ask humidity
and men and the self-help piece is kind
of interesting because John Vicki calls
they ecology of practices right and and
I know like back in the return of King
days they they talked about like you
know you got to get your finances or you
got to get game you got to get like
deadlift and it was purposed towards
like being a better man or getting women
or whatever but but now it seems like
that ecology of practices is well suited
to maintain maintain one sovereignty in
this liminal state so is interesting
that that how that trajectory occurred
so I just wanted to curious if you had
any thoughts on that well you know I
keep saying I'm I'm both I'm a product
of today right like I'm tuned to what's
going on and I'm also a product of it so
I was born my online life was born in
that universe and you're absolutely
right like to focus on your personal
strength and fitness
your financial independence emotion and
mental control mindset control yourself
talk all these things were and I don't
sure of my audience so forgive me if I
going to offend anybody with this but
the reason the manosphere existed in the
first place is because of the crisis of
masculinity and attack on masculinity
there is an ongoing decades-long war on
masculinity and if someone wants to get
into the details and the numbers I can
share those with you there has been an
ongoing feminization of science and the
economy there has been ongoing
de-risking of the economy and of
politics and all these things are tied
together I discovered that that which
upsets the bedroom in our personal
relationships is also the same thing
that's disrupting our economy and our
politics and they're all tied together
and one of the answers and one of the
answers for me and for a lot of my guys
is to focus on developing a new sense of
positive masculinity and using that as a
foundation to improve ourselves our
family our community and the nation
they're all tied together they're all
tied together and because of it it's
wild to me that the the answers that we
came up with 10 12 15 years ago which by
the way are not new right these are
like old-time stuff ancient wisdom but
that has been lost right and it needed
to be refined Andrea dressed for today
and put into terms that we can
understand the answers to solve the
crisis of masculinity are also some of
the answers to solve the crisis in our
political sphere today so it's to me
it's all linked and it's all been part
of one journey for me I started pulling
the thread for me this all started when
I got divorced in 2009 I started pulling
the thread and I've been pulling the
same thread and has led me to this
conversation right here so to me I don't
it's no great leap it's all it's all
perfectly connected hmm yeah question
you know it was good yeah the question
that's coming up is sort of like I
imagine putting myself in your shoes
when you your your back story about kind
of like the you know losing your job and
all the type of stuff there do there's
like a felt sense resentment would
emerge like any anger like a fuck you
anger towards the blue church or whoever
kind of like that construct would place
and put in this place so I'm curious how
that you dealt with that energy may be
transmuted it and how it's currently
present that's a great question
that's a great question so there's
multiple layers to that yes there's
definitely fuck you energy which is
about not losing like I can't be
defeated that's part of it right like
I'm not gonna let an Tifa like
legitimately antifa there's not like a
it's not like me guessing right it was
like the actual flag on her banner
Twitter header leader of DC and Tifa
made it a point to ruin my life
okay and I got investigated and fired
and all this shit my name dragged
through the mud there definitely a sense
of I can't I can't be defeated I'm not
gonna let them win so that's that's one
element and I've been able to transmute
as you say that energy into just trying
to be proactive
the second thing is that there's an
we're not gonna solve the cultural
issues or political issues at least I'm
not by like writing papers and and you
know trying to lobby Congress right this
is this is a top this is a bottom-up
solution and so I wanted to my response
to this and and channeling my anger and
direction into something productive is
to is to get out of that all that and to
go deep in private and secure in a high
trust so we can build communities to
have roots and they have actual impact
and there's definitely a sense of anger
but it has dissipated you know that was
I got docs in January 2018
I'll admit that the 12 months following
that were really tough you know imagine
you're 43 years old and your whole
reputations up in smoke your grant
undergrad graduate degree 20 years on
your resume none of it means anything
anymore because when somebody searches
your name it says that you're some sort
of Nazis complete nonsense but it's out
there it's it's very difficult to defend
against so this is my reaction right
this is my fighting back this is my way
of quote getting revenge but I don't see
it in a negative light like that up
because I see us in doing something very
positive for people and the amount of
positive feedback I've gotten from my
audience you know thirty forty thousand
people on Twitter thousands of people
have read my book
two hundred eyes in the limb order the
the just endless amount of positive
feedback I get tells me that I'm doing
something that is good for people and
good for good for the country good for
the world hopefully that doesn't carry
with it that that spite they might think
and and I do appreciate that question
because it's good for me to consider my
motivations at the same time so thanks
so I'll hand it over to the Q&A in a
moment but another question is coming up
I saw this tweet quite liked and it was
word it was pithy is like the virus
broke woke and I'm curious what you
think about that if the whole kind of
the social justice warrior you know the
meta tribe what is their power dynamics
what's the power dynamics like in this
liminal space that we're in
yeah that's a good question I think
right now it's only been a couple you
know it's only been what a month or so a
bit really being in the news so it the
most definitive thing we can say that is
put a pause on it right like I feel like
the the traffic in those areas and those
words and those those battles has slowed
but then again everything else is paused
- right so it's gonna be hard to say
maybe I'm hopeful that the virus broke
the woke maybe I'm hopeful about that it
has I think for a lot of us hoping you
know put us in a situation of
prioritizing what is important what's
valuable where should we be spending our
attention but I do suspect unfortunately
that because of the pervasiveness of
woke thinking and academia critical Siri
everywhere
social justice warriors everywhere
corporations media you know it HR
everywhere you know my before the virus
my thought was it was gonna take decades
even to work that stuff out of the
system so to the extent that this may
accelerate things a little bit I would
I'll be hopeful but you know once we get
back to some semblance of normal even if
it doesn't look like it did you know two
months ago I have a feeling that a lot
of that stuff is gonna come back and how
we're seeing some of it in the way that
people are calling them the virus racist
I mean it's how a virus can be racist it
can impact people differently but it's
not like it's choosing to do so but
anyway I do I do have hope for that but
at the same time you know that woke shit
is really embedded in our culture right
now cool so I'm gonna hand it over to QA
but I think it's prudent for me to say
this so I think it's safe to say you're
my most controversial I guess so far the
vast OA I imagine because I'm using I'm
viewing this dough as a digital campfire
for anyone to come and we might have you
know intersectional feminist coming to
speak here we have all sorts of people
nomadic tribes coming here and I'm
welcoming them as long as they respect
kind of the space and the fire that's
burning
but I'm thinking just being prudent
right now so if someone's triggered
they're emotionally sensitive in the
audience about something that was said
you can feel free to ask a question
Jacqueline loves being challenged but no
more than one follow up question I'm
just gonna cut it off at that justice up
that kind of framing parameter because
it's not just going to be some messy
debate it's gonna form or anything like
that so with that preface Daniel his
engine could you unmute yourself yeah
first of all Jack thank you so much for
sharing I'm not I'm feeling like that
you have like this earnest like
groundedness in the way that you speak
that you're genuinely trying to say what
you believe to be true and I really
appreciate that
this question I don't know if you're
actually the right person for me to ask
it to so feel free to this sidestep it
but it emerged as you were talking I'm
wondering if you have any insights on
the role of the positive feminine I've
heard Jordan Hall allude to the
particular importance of the feminine to
rise up in response to the meta crisis
and I'm partial to your diagnosis that
there has been some sort of attack on
masculinity I don't know if I'd use
those words in particular but there's
something resonant about that it's
another way to praise it that you might
be able to respond to is where do you
see the limits of the positive masculine
in the current crisis yeah that's a very
good question in you know perhaps Jordan
Peterson might be better to feel this
one I know that they you know is very
into the notion of the Great Mother and
like all things so you know masculinity
can exist without femininity it's yin
and yang and I think you need equal
parts the words Berrien singh right now
is like any disequilibrium and and i
would even argue that there is also a
crisis of femininity as well there's
there's been a great just general
neutering of gender expression or the
archetypical experiences of who we are
based on our biology and our experiences
and in my book I really explore a lot of
these questions about determinism versus
blank slate and what how essential is
our biology to our behavior and
therefore into our society and our
structures and you know I wouldn't I
would never say that we don't need from
an in fact we need it we need it just as
much as we need
of masculinity we need we need as
champions for both and I feel like what
happened over the last 20 30 40 years is
that there has become no no champion for
either the the sense of a traditional
and you can define this however you want
femininity was sort of cast aside for a
champion of a male ideal but then at the
same time for men that male ideal was
diminished and and pushed aside and
devalued so in fact we've we've got both
pushing the wrong and up and pushing the
right down at the same time and we need
to sort of reimburse at as far as I know
and and I don't ever put a value on
either one as being higher or lower
they're essential repairs were designed
to be complementary not to compete with
each other and I would just like a
little bit more honesty about that right
an honesty and embracing our differences
you know like as the name escaping made
the gentleman from Google who wrote the
memo James do more James the more wrote
that memo where all he did was cite a
bunch of like commonly accepted
psychological studies about the
differences in our tendencies group
differences and you saw what happened to
him you know fired and then also it
revealed within Google
you know how far from you know accepting
of basic basic reality they were and
they control our access to information
and so it that seems you know sort of
mindset is permeating not only just our
relationships but our technology and the
algorithms in the way that we search for
data and the data that's presented to us
and and so I again I would stress mutual
benefit for both yin and a yang
complimentary and not putting a value
judgment on either one but just
stressing the fact that we needs a
champion them both
cool thank you no thank you for that
complimentary earlier - appreciate it
um Rachel haywire it's a good question
follow-up question right so it's it's
always tough to tell what is like online
posturing which is what versus what is
reality and who's trying to glom on to
certain social media phenomena you know
but I think in general I support and
believe in women's choices to do
whatever they want to do whether that's
trying to be CEO corporation or to stay
home in home school five kids and - so
all their own clothes and you know do
local farming and whatever so I think
that a response to this extended period
of feminism radical feminism and I don't
mean equality like I believe in equality
of rights for everybody etc etc this
sort of next-level mutation that we're
into now I think that's a natural
pushback just like them the rise of the
manosphere was a national natural
pushback also a rise of traditional
wives or traditional women are
traditional femininity it will also be a
sort of a natural pushback so i unsee
prized by it i question anybody's
branding and stuff you know Daniel you
pointed out that I have a sense of
authenticity about me which i think is
how I've been able to build an audience
like I've never set forth to like brand
myself in a particular way it's just all
natural evolution of Who I am but the
the trad Wives stuff you know it's hard
to tell you know how much of it is just
LARPing and how much of it is for real
but I do I do support that kind of
thinking and I do think it's look if you
have to ask yourself or ask yourself
he's a world and which is extreme I
always like to make these extreme
cases but a world in which you've got
you know women in their late 30s and
early 40s who were who wish they had
families but instead have careers versus
women in their late 30s early 40s that
have families and wish they had careers
I'm not sure which which world would you
rather have I I think that I prefer the
one that focuses on the family and
raises children and keeps them out of
the clutches of our you know some of our
more you know pernicious public
education scenarios etc and just give
people a place to transmit their own
values to their children rather than
allowing other people to do it for them
alright we've got a bunch of juicy
questions rolling in now so um so Sam
wants me to read this one on his behalf
how do you uh also the lumina order
yourself see the next five years
unfolding are you guys prepping for a
collapse social economic ecological or a
positive reset on the in the mid
long-term yeah that's a great question
if you would have asked me that it's two
months ago I would have had a totally
different answer for you much more
definitive right now the chess pieces
are being moved around in a way that's
gonna preclude any predictions of the
next three to five years it's entirely
possible that we're gonna see it a
twenty to thirty to forty percent
annualised reduction in GDP in the
second quarter okay we have when have we
ever lived through anything like that we
have absolutely no idea what's gonna
come we don't know how the economy is
gonna respond how the economy is going
to bounce back we don't know to what
extent our personal liberties are going
to be semi-permanently you know violated
through whatever precautions that we
have to take I mean we're all sitting at
home right now because the government
ordered us to do that right I mean yeah
we're home cuz we don't want to get sick
but at the same time personal liberties
are in question I really have no idea
what's going to happen we are prepping
in the sense that we have United
ourselves into a tribe a group of people
a network that sees the world similarly
we share information and tactics and
strategies and even finances and
resources you know we've had
guys made guys somebody who's in this
shed actually send you know he had a
back supply of masks and sent them to
our people on the front lines and we've
got people we share financial resources
with each other and times of crisis and
needs so we're we're preparing for the
future in that way by doubling down with
our organization our fraternal network
our professional network what is gonna
really have no idea and you can tell
that I'm not the only one because the
markets are in turmoil businesses are in
turmoil governments are in turmoil our
health organizations are in turmoil
everything everything right now I mean
if there was ever a liminal moment I
hate so the name of the group is living
order right because two months ago it
was very we accepted that we were in a
state of liminality due to the change in
technology social media information
distribution at the end of the top-down
you know information network or
distribution channels but now our we're
in like 10x liminal state the economy
the financial network the financial
system culture society civil liberties
health the way that we just socialized
and spent time everything is in flux and
we are clearly in the wilderness between
two points of stability and to anyone
that says that they know what's gonna
happen in the next 12 18 24 months is
lying to you the only reasonable
perspective and posture at this point in
time is I have no idea so what do you do
to prepare for that meditate work out
get strong build a community build a
network build a team get with a good
team and then together you can figure
out how to navigate so one of the one of
the issues and I wrote down the wrote
this down it and get to it was Oh de
dooda dooda so that's that's that's
basically our philosophy is our the OODA
loop is a way of orienting to the world
and then changing and then adapting
right and our goal is to create a system
where the goal isn't an outcome a
specific outcome but rather designing
for emergence this is with title one of
my
chess was and designing a system where
we iterate faster than anybody else
that's the goal that's that's the only
thing that we can do right now is figure
out how to iterate faster so that we can
adapt to the changing environments and
the changing information flow and then
figure out what to do I have no idea
what it's going to be like so in the
meantime I'm just gonna tune up my
instrument at best I can and to build a
system that provides answers at the time
that the answers reveal themselves
that's awesome
okay Tyson hey I'm curious about some of
the main challenges or obstacles have
kept you from growing beyond 200 and the
liminal order so far and like to what
extent it might you feel that it could
be optimal so I'll keep it to a limited
quantity like Dunbar's number for
example and people you can have proper
clearance and then maybe just add on to
that like in the early stages like when
you were before well before 200 like
what was like a starting point of a
number of members so I guess something
going and happening and yeah it's like
what you learned from that or what is in
you see is like an optimal group - yes
surprising right so there's a bunch of
things there yeah it's very difficult to
maintain personal relationships over a
certain amount whether it's 150 or
whatever or whether you count the ones
that are online or your personal ones or
your family it is hard to maintain a
huge number of personal relationships
but the the limiting factor for us right
now is communication technology we
haven't figured out the right software
or the right application that's gonna
allow us to incorporate too many more
people you know it's a si over 500 or
something like that at this point the
goal within the liminal order though is
to is and I brainstormed about this
quite a bit and I haven't come up with
the right word yet I want to call it
atomizing but that's not really it it's
sort of like creating micro universes
within so there's power to network right
with a certain point each additional
member to the network doesn't just
at plus one yeah you know the all the
relationships it's greater than one so
each person you add the marginal return
is even bigger than just one person so
you want to have a network that brings a
new network power right but you get
limited through infrastructure
bottlenecks and you get limited by when
the signal-to-noise ratio changes so
what I've encouraged guys in a little
more order to do and there's a number of
them here in the chat right now is to
create sub groups and sub universes
within so we're united overall through a
similar worldview we can participate at
large in in large group sessions and
large group events but then the real
deeper personal connections come from
the micro ization or atomization or just
keeping your groups sort of small within
within the larger organization and and
we're working on building that kind of
culture right now and it's a it's a
different little it's a different
mindset for some people but we take on
you know maybe 30 or 40 or 50 people
every couple of months digest them into
the system get everybody acclimated and
part of it also is really just sort of
preserving the culture right if we
brought in 500 people all at once then
the culture just becomes whatever those
people are bringing with them whereas is
we trickle people through our onboarding
processes is extensive and you don't
just get thrown in there you have to go
through a whole system of things we're
trying to really get them to adapt into
our culture so we can preserve the
culture itself so it's strategic growth
rather than just growth for growth's
sake at this point but eventually we're
also going to need some new some new
tech so we're looking at Herbet we're
looking at dry i/o we're looking at a
few ways to code and create our own
systems that are completely independent
and off the main networks as well - so
here's a question I'm going to read it
and it's anonymous so you know is going
to be good or they asked to be anonymous
so I'm interested in the type of private
and public narratives that will emerge
from your militia or your order if you
have an exclusive group of yeah
that's a question so private public
narratives that emerge from our
exclusive group well the private
narrative that saved a bunch of lives
and money in the last couple of months
was like hey this Corona thing is gonna
be a big deal you better get your she
better get your shit in order and that
narrative was ahead of the others so we
were definitely at least three or four
weeks in advance and we put out posture
papers and position papers to our to our
community that allow people to get to
get to get prepared in terms of what
we're going to put out publicly I'm
looking at my buddy here right now we're
still we're still trying to figure out
to what extent we're going to engage
publicly it's really really the goal is
about us as individuals within this
network to create a grassroots movement
that's going to mature and evolve in
into positions of power where you can
make change on the margins you know
that's that sort of our goal is just the
same way the blue church raised people
up and got them you know and
indoctrinated that's a bad word I'm not
going to use that word but you know what
I mean and in it to positions of power
where they're able to have high leverage
impact on society that's sort of our
goal too but that's going to take a long
time right that's gonna take time and in
the meantime we're gonna worry about
ourselves and our families in our
community and that's our leverage there
the relationship with the public is one
that we haven't figured out just yet and
again I haven't come to this knowing the
answers I'm trying to design a system
that's going to surface the best answer
the collective answer for us and you
know design something that will allow
allow the right thing to emerge rather
than for me to just start off saying
it's going to be this you know that's
too rigid that's not what this world is
about right now right this world is
about iterating and iterating the
iterating and bringing in trying to
absorb as much of this information as
you can and try try to do the right
thing and adjust on the fly so that's
that's what we're going with
dan you had a question that was similar
but I liked the framing of it would you
like to ask it to Jack sure I asked two
questions which is the first or the
second the the most recent one about the
optimal grip on reality okay first of
all I want to thank you jack for for
speaking with us today I appreciate your
sincerity and the good faith that you're
coming forward in this dialogue my
question is given the isolated culture
that you are developing what are you
doing if anything to reach out to other
cultures to ensure that you maintain an
optimal grip on reality that's okay
that's a good question the scott adams
in me says what is reality and what is
optimal right so there's there's a lot
there's a lot there if we're getting the
outcomes that we want then we're
optimizing our sense in our grip on
reality that's one sort of throwaway
comment which you can write a book on
the the more practical answer to your
question is that most all of us within
hello are also outwardly tuned into
massive social media networks mass media
academia politics corporate world
finance technology so the way we're
we're all engaged with outside we're all
engaged with the outside world and we're
all taking the information that we get
from the outside world and bringing it
into the limo order and then processing
and analyzing it for ourselves and for
our members so work work continued we're
not disconnected from from reality in
that sense and/or from the the larger
culture as it were we are have created
our own culture that's for sure and we
did that because we see it as something
that's beneficial but you know the the
way that we stay connected is by having
everybody experiencing their own
universe their own their own culture
their own communities and what reach and
not and then bringing it in and then we
process and analyze it and then move
forward the outreach that we do in the
mortar as someone just mentioned is on
an individual basis anyway so where we
would these are like you know your
friends or your colleagues or your
associates or someone that you know
online social media you reach out to
them and you invite them and you explain
what we're doing and so there is a sense
of outreach but really where we're
meeting a demand there's so many people
out there that are hunger hungry for
community right that's like one of the
first things that we're offering
community is a way to connect with
people actually care about you and one
of the things that we didn't even talk
about here is I mentioned it in passing
is but we're like a mutual aid Society
at the same time we've had guys go
through crisis where they lose their job
or the wife you know well then their
children dies or you know his wedding is
in doubt and you just instantly snap to
and raised thousands of dollars and sent
it to them within an hour you know and
like save the day save the day for them
in some small way that we could you know
so this is about building personal
relationships in a way where you know
that the common worldview is there first
right so for a lot of us you know we're
right-of-center
mostly Trump supporters definitely part
of the red insurgency totally anti blue
Church etc most of us are high
concentrations are DC New York Austin
San Francisco so we're already living in
isolation and sort of stressful fear and
like you can't talk at work and you
can't share your ideas with your
neighbors and you can't you have to
whisper when how did bars and
restaurants and whatever and so this is
this is fulfilling a real sense of like
I need brothers right like I need men
that I can relate to and depend on and
care about brotherly love right like
there's definitely a sense of love and
compassion and empathy that we've
fostered for each other so it's it's all
these things that we're talking about it
from sense making and all that stuff all
the way just down to like man I just
need I need a brother to love and to
love me back
where you start with this common
worldview which is a novel way of
organizing community because in the past
it's been oh you're my college roommate
or oh you work next door to me in the
office or oh you live next door to me
but none of those things ensure the fact
that you're gonna see the world the same
way or have the same concerns or it seem
the same passions that way with this
group we can start with the passions in
the worldview and then fill form the
personal relationships from the personal
relationships after that cool so this
will be the last question
Malcom Ocean can you ask your shorter
version of your question
[Music]
yeah I mean basically just like I'm
noting that in your cultural context
it's like naturally it was coming out of
this sort of Manos to your thing but
that there could also be liminal teams
that are coming from a different
cultural context and and you know I'm
I'm part of another one that also has
liminal in the name and but you know
isn't is based on a completely different
culture but it seems to me that we have
some shared cultural platform so I guess
I'm wondering like what do you see as
possible collaborations between liminal
teams that might have different cultural
contexts in collectively transcending
the culture wars so it's like maybe you
guys are helping people get out of the
anger and fight of the manosphere but
then the right piece of other people who
are helping social justice warriors
become like less rayji and more based on
integrity as well I'm just I'm
interested in your take on that yeah
well I think I'm doing it right now you
know this is this is exactly the way
that I see these things evolving and and
outreach and just trying to cross over
networks and try to share information I
mean one thing that popped into my mind
is I mean sure we could like produce
like a tech product or something that
facilitated this kind of stuff but you
know more importantly it's is having
these cross pollinating conversations
you know the form and of this
conversation here I found to be very
beneficial I'm going to take some of
this with me back to my conversations
I'm usually a facilitator in these
zooom chats like this so there's there's
ways for us to cross pollinate and to
reach out and to share and compare notes
and you know networks working with
networks is just one bigger network you
know and of itself right so I think it's
important that we all just keep talking
which is another reason why I'm always
hoping to talk to anybody
basically because these conversations
are very powerful they helped us evolve
our thinking I mean just just the fact
that Jordan Hall decided to come talk to
me and then share and we related and
then we had a follow up that that was
part of the genesis for a liminal order
which now has 200 guys which has changed
lives across the country which in mound
in powerful ways so the conversations
there it's easy to just look at this and
be like oh it's just a bunch of people
talking on the internet but no man if
you're paying attention and you're
engaged and you're putting out your
energy and you're receptive to other
people's energy you synthesize that and
then in two weeks or a month you have an
idea that percolates up into your
consciousness and then you take action
and you build something and then all of
a sudden you're having real-world impact
and you're you're helping people and it
all came from the talk that you had you
know three months ago so these these
kinds of experiences are very important
and that's why I'm here and I want to
keep doing it and I'm just really
grateful that you guys had me and on
that I had a conversation with Jerry
James in Jason Snyder yesterday when we
actually were gossiping about who does
America mediate jack with but a metaphor
came up they're like there's gonna be
all these digital campfires that emerge
and then you know we'd be able to see
each other and we visit each other's
campfires so like you know Jack visited
the store this campfire I'll be happy to
visit his if he ever invites me
definitely
so yeah so I'll uh I'll close in the
moment but you want to have any closing
thoughts jacket where people can find
you or not find you
the best way to find me is on Twitter at
Jack Murphy live and then there's Jack
Murphy live.com as well and then liminal
- order - order comm you can sign up for
the mailing list there we send out a
bunch of stuff but really you know the
best place to find me is on Twitter and
I continue to engage there because it is
the best way for me to reach reach new
people and to bring them into the the
greater network and then we move them in
a little bit closer and then a little
bit closer and then into the core group
so we're always looking to expand the
greater network and really such
thoughtful questions and earnest faces I
really appreciate it and you know Peters
has really been a lot of fun and you
know thank you guys very much it's been
great very cool so I'll make some
announcements in a moment about upcoming
events but Jack thank you so much for
coming on my friend that was lovely
thanks everyone for the excellent
questions so I'll talk about the couple
upcoming events this evening we have a 7
p.m. eastern time we have saw critic
speed-dating with Raven Connolly and
we're combining speed dating with the
Socratic method
I fully an invite jack and hope he comes
to that one and tomorrow we have a
loving cringe meditation I think that is
at 2:00 p.m. Eastern Time so we're all
gonna watch that celebrity sing-along
imagine we're gonna feel cringe and
judgement in our body and then we're
going to shine love on that as a
spiritual exercise and also / artistic
performance and then Daniel cos engine
he's doing similar to the liminal order
what the limit order has already
established he's doing a metagame
mastermind out of the stoah so Daniel if
you're here do you understand mute
yourself and just talk a little about it
sure yeah so we're doing a prototyping
session to find out how we can create
digital gangs to help people cultivate
personal sovereignty and respond to the
meta crisis something that I think is
particularly important right now because
everybody's socially isolated so this is
a week - and it's gonna be a recurring
session at 6 p.m. here at the stoah and
that's yesterday's yeah that's easier
time cool lastly the the stoah is here
as a gift for all of us to use in this
time of need if you're inspired to
provide a gift to the stoah just go
the website in order to gift economy at
the bottom of the page all right thanks
everyone thank you guys I really
appreciate it
take care